by the way we're in the middle of the
Perfection of giving okay and we're
going to discuss
giving and it says means uh people who
have nothing people who don't have much
money so D bu bu means uh bugs okay Dr
means
ants uh this is a thing I used to do
with Lama Christi we used to go
McDonald's and uh the only thing we
could eat there was the French fries the
salad at that time was worse than the
hamburgers and
uh and uh we would buy french fries and
go sit outside and feed the birds you
know and uh it's really fun it's a fun
meditation so you buy something small
and then you sit outside and feed the
birds and uh
you hold it in your hand and the birds
come and then um you talk to the birds
and you say if if you eat this uh you're
going to be my student when I become a
Buddha you know and then you throw them
a piece of french fry and they always
eat
it okay who else did
that huh yeah well yeah but Lord Buddha
gave the body to to the to the tiger
cups right he said if you eat this then
you're going to be my students and those
five were his first students the four
babies and the
mom and it's a I don't know I think it's
really fun there's a lot of fun ways you
can do the paramas you know the bodh
activities you don't have to be very
serious and you know try to remember
your 64 vows and all this okay you can
have fun with it also
and I think uh if you have fun with it
you'll be better at it you'll be a
better bodh sappa okay so think about
ways that you can have fun and and do
things for other beings and have fun and
you can do it all day long okay you can
do it uh just when you see people on the
way in the airport just do funny little
good things for them okay let them go in
line first let them use the toilet
that's clean stuff like that if you can
find one
okay means you know a little bit of
barley
flour this is the Perfection of giving
this is the practice of the Perfection
of giving you don't have to
think that I have to give my body or
something like that just little things
is fun little
things with remembering that you're
supposed to be a bodh sappa is probably
more productive for us it's probably
better practice for
us then
that's
means daughter or son of the Buddhas
okay and it's a synonym for bodh sappa
okay you see right right
uh he
says you know sit there if there's too
many birds and one french fry it's not
enough then buy a second french fry you
know like when you do a little practice
like that for
some animals or something uh make sure
they are satisfied okay make sure they
get what they want
you know keep throwing them french fries
until they refuse to eat
more okay all right and SBA SBA means uh
make sure they they get what they want
okay since it's just pieces of french
fries you can do it with money it's a
little difficult okay
means uh we
feel like we're big people when we give
something when we make a donation to
Diamond
Mountain you know we think oh we're
we're so special and I'm so generous you
know and uh we tend to have some pride
about even small things that we give so
he says uh that's m jimba madaka means
uh you
you made your practice of the first
Perfection dirty okay you made it dirty
by being proud about it just give it and
shut up okay and shut up in your own
heart you know don't don't think I'm so
special I'm so good you know I give all
this money okay personally I find that
it's good to forget it as soon as you
give it just give it and then look ahead
to the next one you know and don't don't
dwell on the old ones
okay here's an important advice
traditional this next part is
traditionally very
important sometimes you get excited
when uh the people at Diamond Mountain
like sunum
are fundraising and they get you excited
and you give a lot and then you go home
and you say God that was too much
money I shouldn't have given Aldo so
much you
know and Rob's like G your backpack's
getting
empty and then uh there's a very
strong tradition in the L room that you
should never
regret uh something you did okay it's
true Maybe you gave too
much uh maybe you overdid it but uh
never regret what you gave when you
regret it you kind of traditionally they
say you destroy the Good Karma okay the
seed is
damaged uh when you regret it so you
it's okay to say look I was excited I
gave too much and that's okay next time
I'll be more
careful but uh but don't reg don't
regret what you gave and and don't try
to get it back or something
just just let it go okay just let it
go and by the way later you will not
regret it you will be very happy about
it
okay and if you just give away stuff
uncontrollably you know all day
long uh it's it feels great okay and and
you will get much more back don't worry
okay just get in the
habit of giving whatever you can you
know and and do it all day and my
personal experience is uh it will just
keep coming back and you'll
be crazy you have much more money than
you ever thought of okay it'll just keep
coming it's crazy and just enjoy it and
use it okay
[Music]
M there's a special weird karma when you
find out the person you gave the money
to had a lot of money
already that happened to me one
time and uh I was pretty
upset and uh but just let it go it's
okay and uh try to check it out
beforehand uh but we never know
sometimes people have a lot of money
already and we don't know and they ask
you for money and it's okay okay if they
have a lot of money and they ask you for
money they probably need
it okay because
they're something inside they feel like
they don't have enough or something okay
so the main thing is uh after you
give in English we say second guess
don't don't don't say maybe I did the
wrong thing thing or maybe I gave too
much or something like that then you
kind of ruin the karma okay so just give
it and don't worry about it
okay it always comes back much more than
you think always always okay uh if you
regret it or
you if you if you think oh I gave too
much you know uh you ruin it
okay okay
is a nice word in the second line means
to fix
something and uh the word shastra
shastra denture right
Tim uh the word for a classical
commentary in Buddhism is
fixer okay uh it fixes you and this CH
means uh fix your motivation
uh before you give something so
pause always think uh I would like you
to be my student when I become a Buddha
okay like even you just give somebody a
few dollars or you give them a cup of
coffee or something just just pause in
your own mind and say I you know please
be my student when I become a Buddha
please be my student there's a beautiful
uh
we just finished s's text and there was
a beautiful uh
prayer at the end uh he
said in the Realms of Hell may people
may I appear and may people ask me to be
their teacher in hell and may I sit in
hell with the beings and and be their
teacher and this very beautiful okay so
when you give
anything uh make a prayer that I should
be your teacher
okay make those prayers sh means
uh like you almost feel like you want to
cry or
something there was good
so there's a
uh when you see emptiness
directly
uh during the that 20 minutes
um you don't see other things you cannot
see other things uh because you can only
see emptiness so you you can't even see
yourself uh for 20 minutes uh then when
you come
out you have
a like a until you sleep
maybe
maybe 10 or 12 hours more you have all
these amazing uh ideas okay those are
not not the direct perception emptiness
those are we call uh after effects or or
you start having
amazing understandings for the rest of
the day by the way the next day is kind
of
dead but that day try not to go to sleep
okay and uh one of the things uh you
realize and there's many many things
those
uh understandings that you have because
Prana is still in your central channel
right uh some Prana is still in your
central channel so some of the ideas you
have all of those
ideas uh were organized into the four
ARA truths okay four aspects of the four
truths 16 different cool ideas okay and
they got kind of corrupted and they got
to be Doctrine and they got to be this
boring list and it it doesn't seem to
make much sense and um but there
are the point is there's certain
amazing uh understandings you have after
you see emptiness directly because
you're The Prana is still in the central
channel so you you have for example you
can read other people's minds until the
end of the day but uh here one of the
understandings you have and maybe we
should rewrite the 16 I don't know but
one of the understandings you
have is that you
never did uh you never did any giving to
another person without
selfishness you never ever in your life
you never
really gave something to someone not
expecting some kind of you know reward
or praise or something like that it's
human nature there's always whenever you
give something to
somebody until you're a
pretty strong ARA there's always
some motivation that you want something
or you're trying to get something and uh
I think it's I don't think you should
walk around depressed about it but you
should understand it it's it's if you
have a bad
habit at least you should understand it
right even if you can't stop it so uh I
think you
should understand that habit that we
tend to we don't tend to give something
unless we can get something and uh so if
there's situations where you can give
anonymously or um you
can you know run away after you give the
thing that's sweet okay and you're not
going to change your human nature before
you become an Arya you're not going to
change but uh at least know about it and
then uh later you can work on it okay so
it's it's human
nature not to do something for someone
else without some self-interest okay
there it's human nature it's okay but we
have to think someday may I may may I
someday may I perfect giving may I
really give without anything coming back
or without any
hope I should be doing pictures I guess
uh 19 4619 it's the person giving
holding out a hand keep going I
think somebody's holding a hand out I
don't know there you go okay CH Jim
means he's going to talk about
the the bodh SATA first Perfection
giving Dharma okay giving teachings to
someone and uh I put in the
Bold
chin it's too bad you can't talk because
you could make some
money exception Tim can they talk if I
ask them a
question
okay for
$100
[Music]
y looks like I'm
safe nen means to listen right du means
they want
to CH soand Chen means uh when we talk
about
the gift of the Dharma in
Buddhism uh yend chin
means don't give it to people who don't
want
it okay uh don't bother people with your
Buddhism okay you know don't grab people
and say did you hear the good news you
know about Buddha you know don't don't
bother people with your Buddhism and I
think when you
first start studying there's a habit
especially with your wife or your
husband or your your relatives and you
say
oh GUI Michael is the true prophet and
and uh he he gave us these wonderful
things and you have to agree and you
know if you want your wife or husband
never to become a Buddhist the best
thing is to bother them with your
Buddhism okay so don't bother other
people with your Buddhism and don't
don't try to push it on people who don't
want to hear it okay you
can be a Buddhist and affect people you
know be generous for
example uh and people will watch you but
don't try to sell Buddhism to people
okay if somebody wants to
know if somebody wants to know they're
interested then you can if you just
teach them a single
verse you know a line or two lines of
Buddhism
uh that's that is the gift of the Dharma
that is the karma of giving the the gift
of the Dharma which is probably the
highest form of giving
okay I have in my own life sort of a
what do you call
it uh priority conflict you know so I
have time you know I have choice of
doing I have choices I have to I can
translate more books I can teach more
things a lot of people
want personal things or you know and I
have to decide with my own time you know
I only have a limited time so I I have
to make decisions every day about who
how do I spend the time time and uh I
think
um I think to keep the Dharma alive is
priority for me you know to make sure it
doesn't disappear in the
world uh is sometimes uh I I I think
about it a lot people ask me sometimes
people need like two hours three hours
discussion about a personal problem or
something and I'm like and I have this
struggle in my mind I'm like I know they
really need the
time but
uh but I my time is not is not unlimited
I only have so many hours and then I'll
be going somewhere so I have to think
about what's more important or how can I
help more people so uh here it says uh
if you get a chance to share the Dharma
that's the highest gift I think you can
think about that when
you're uh thinking about priorities you
know if there's some way to keep the
Dharma in the world that's really
important okay they call it the light of
the world
right and I I always heard that in
Christian you know this you you should
be don't hide the light under a basket
right they say Jesus said that and uh
that this
world without these teachings
would be Darkness I think there would be
no light in this world so uh I think you
have
to personally I think I have to keep the
some light going you know before I go I
got to make sure there's some light okay
and that means I don't always have time
to uh to sit and listen for an hour or
something like I just don't have time
there's 200 100,000 students
now people say I just need an hour guess
you know and I'm like
did you learn math in school they say
yeah and I say what is 1 time
200,000 and they say 200,000 I'm like
it's right I still need an hour and I'm
like okay but we have about 200,000
students in the whole system then uh
it's imp it's completely impossible I
don't have this capacity I can't do it
you know so don't I have to make
choices and I think to keep to keep
the to keep the physical Dharma in the
world is is a something I I'm capable of
so I think I have to try to do that
okay
uh if you just share a line with another
person in the
class uh you are teaching the Dharma
okay if you just explain
you know something that somebody said in
the class then you even if it's just uh
on the in the car going to Tucson or
something then that's that's the same as
teaching up on on the stage okay same
thing to share the Dharma with one other
person personally is the same as giving
a Dharma teaching okay he says not
me uh next picture
I like this picture
uh this is Lama Palma she
uh she came for a job to my jewelry
company many years ago and
um uh we were working long hours I
remember Uma Thurman came in the same
week uh and asked for a job I
interviewed um Thurman
and I said my advice to you is you know
go be an
actress because you will never be a
secretary and her father often thanks me
uh but llama pelma came at the same time
and U and we were working till midnight
every day we were just building the
company and it was really hard and uh
and I said look I'll hire you but
there's no hours okay you work as long
as I
say and she says
no the first thing she said to me was
no and I'm
like there's a long line of people
waiting for a job interview and I'm like
I would just throw her out you know I
just say well thank you very much you
know I'll get in touch you know but
something told me to keep her and I said
that'll be fun
and uh you can work whatever hours you
want and and
uh then she uh then she started coming
to classes stuff like that and she
became a a great
teacher and then uh if you walk around
her neighborhood in New York every
single person is stopping and talking to
her and they know her because she was
teaching so many people everywhere and
um and then we started to call her Lama
pelma and then people objected she's not
Tibetan she's not a
man she doesn't wear robes you know
she's not
from Asia she's how can you call her
llama we got all this uh trouble from
people and
um here the text says okay the greatest
llama says
you don't have to be
sitting up on a Dharma throne in front
of a bunch of Asians to be a
llama okay that he says not me okay Lama
s means uh the name llama means you're
teaching people it doesn't matter what
country you're from doesn't
before my teachers time and my time uh
women were not allowed to study the G
course can you imagine can you believe
it and and when we started teaching
women we got a lot of trouble we got a
lot of criticism and
uh and uh it was hard it was really
hard means to climb up on a Dharma
Throne okay it's not necessarily the
case that you have to climb up on a
Dharma Throne to teach the Dharma you
could be sitting in an airplane seat
next to it's a great place to teach
somebody they have a seat belt on they
can't get
away the bathrooms on the plane are
never
free okay captive audience
Chim Jim Shen Ching this is a simple uh
simple phrase but it's it's nice uh
where are we
next picture we got a video I think you
guys
Francisco is there a video I don't know
I thought there was a
video
maybe no can
yeah he's massaging
it
okay anyway tell me if you do yeah okay
let's go this one of my favorite videos
in here some
Francisco
I'll so
the guar is one of the best s in the
world oh here we go
okay
sound oh oh
must have been
[Music]
100 we know what we have let's hold
on found what we're looking for in
life call us czy but things are finally
right with you and I the few
is
[Music]
bright you and I we got
it we don't need no
[Music]
more even in the hard
time you and I can weather any
stor before I sleep
hear the cricket see the
moon sa tight and through and
through no limit to what we can
do oh we know what we have let's Hold On
Tight found what we're looking for in
life call us crazy but things are
finally right
with you and I the future is
bright
[Applause]
yay uh Chim jimen Chen uh the gift of
the Dharma is the highest gift of all
okay so if you want a good karma or you
want to do something
important uh then to care the Dharma is
the highest gift you can give okay and
it's kind of nice because you don't have
to be
perfect uh don't don't feel like you
have to be perfect imperfect Dharma
teachers are the
best uh because they understand people's
problems you know they say they say I'm
fighting with my husband they say me
too and you so uh you know don't feel
like you have to be some kind of Saint
or something like that okay uh I think
when you teach the
Dharma uh somebody asked me what's the
first thing that happens gisha I said
when you teach the Dharma you reach a
new level of
hypocrisy you know CU you're teaching
something you cannot do yourself you
know and uh but it you know
inevitably if you talk about it all day
it starts to affect you right so uh
don't think you have to be
perfect uh don't wait till you're
perfect it'll wait a long
time okay uh what you understand teach
what you don't understand admit it just
say look I I I'll get I'll get back to
you on that question you know and then
go ask somebody else and don't
be don't think you have to be perfect
don't be
proud uh don't be embarrassed to
you know mess up at a teaching just do
it okay it's the highest Karma you can
do okay and don't be shy you know
somebody you meet on a plane you say
where are you going they say Costa Rica
you say oh I was looking for someone to
sponsor my teaching in Costa
Rica and uh okay don't be shy and and
and don't wait till you're ready and
don't wait until you're perfect because
that's a long time away so you know go
ahead teach we mess up okay teachers
mess
up U don't don't you know mess up once
just shut up and keep going okay and
apologize to everybody and then and then
keep going okay so
uh Grandpa's ready to help with the
second tour okay just let me know okay
before I spend the money
uh you might want to get it this week
actually talk to the guy with the
envelope right
okay
uh probably better to get it this week I
got some money I don't know if I'm gonna
have next week okay uh but I'm happy to
to do the same donation okay all
[Music]
right this this is a nice sentence and I
remember when I first heard it from my
teacher and and I was very happy to hear
about it and and they said um when
you're in doing your morning
practice and when you're saying your
prayers when you're saying your
mantras uh don't Mumble okay like
just you
know you hear people do that right and
he says say it clearly so that someone
sitting next to you could hear okay like
unless you're on an airplane or
something okay so om say it clearly
because there are lots of spirits in the
world especially here I think there's a
lot of spirits hanging around there was
a lot of trouble here uh there was a lot
of fighting between the white people and
the and the
original people here I think there's a
lot of spirits moving around
and and they're curious what you're
doing in your cabin and they want to
listen and so do your prayers loud
enough that they can hear and here's the
original source of that a lot of what I
say in a class comes from this book I
was brought up on this this was the milk
that I was fed on okay P Zen J when
you're reciting your
prayers there are spirits around
you also you have imagined that the
people in the whole world are sitting
with you right uh
therefore imagine that there are many
beings listening because there are and
you cannot see them okay some name CH
Chi chimber this also you will get the
karma of giving the Dharma which is a
very very high Karma okay so if they're
going to listen
anyway so you might as well get some
credit you know say oh I I know you're
listening here's some mantras you can
listen to these are nice mantras I
learned this at di
Mountain okay okay chra
B joke
uh animals uh he says all the way down
to bugs and worms you know animals can
hear you so you know I don't know if
you're releasing an animal or you see an
animal I mentioned uh I I I like to sing
to wild animals you know I like to do
mandala offerings or if I see a DE or
something I'll I'll stop and I'll sing
the Mund offering to them or something
sometimes they run away and they're like
oh and then sometimes they're like you
know and uh so you can put a seat in
their mind so even you meet
a they wanted me to take my
granddaughter to the zoo yesterday day
before and I haven't been to a zoo in 50
years I think it's a terrible thing
and
uh but I said okay I'll go and my wife
said no comments and I'm like understand
you know and so I I went through all the
zoo and and sang to the animals and you
know the giraffe and all those guys and
you can do that when you meet animals
you can whisper stuff or sing things to
them put seeds in their mind okay have
fun this whole thing thing about Dharma
practice you should have fun you should
be
creative and and you should be fun you
should be an odd person you know and
that's fine you know let other people
get used to it you know they they're not
having fun you can say look I know you
don't want to have fun but I want to
have fun and if you think I'm a little
bit strange I'm okay with that you you
can go ahead and think that and i' I've
done that my whole life and it's fine
and it's nice okay you don't have to
show off being weird but you can just
quietly be weird okay and it's fun it's
just fun you know oh that's the guy who
sings to the Giraffe you're like yeah
and and you're like okay bo b joke Bak
joke means you can put seeds in their
mind by singing mandala offering to them
or or something like that okay
Shen okay
J uh Shen means if if you can plant a
seed in an insect by singing to it then
obviously if you
sing somewhere else you know in the park
or something and other people are around
and that's fine just don't get locked up
okay or maybe it's good and you can sing
in there in the jail
uh then there's a big tradition in uh
the monastery don't forget he's talking
to a lot of
monks and there's a big tradition called
trong choke trong choke means
uh people pay the monks to come to sing
prayers at their house and usually you
get a lunch in return so uh you you go
in the morning and you recite at
people's homes and uh then it's supposed
to be that the people sit around and
listen and this is an old Buddhist
tradition so I grew up in a Mongolian
Temple um I was there for 25 years we we
used to do Chong choke couple times a
week and uh it's usually four or five
months and you go to somebody's house
they make a big
lunch and you you recite prayers in
their house and and we had a the Abbot
was this old old Mongolian blind he was
blind and uh and very
chubby uh cuz he loved trong Chong and
uh he say let's go do trong Chong you
know we're like okay and take us and
then I remember one Tong J and he said
um he said we're kind of late you know
we gota we got to start a monks are
supposed to start by 12:00 right
supposed to start eating by 12:00 and
not eat in the
evening so he's like well we're kind of
in a rush today and and he had a he said
well I brought one scripture with me but
uh he said I have an idea let's split it
up and uh I'll give everybody five
pages and then uh we'll recite it you
know and we can eat
faster and uh I'm like but everyone's
going to be reciting a different a
different thing you know and he said
they don't
know and I'm like okay and he gave
everybody five pages and and it was The
Diamond Cutter Sutra and I never read it
uh and I was like wow this is good stuff
you know and uh then every time we went
somewhere I would say I try to get a
different five pages and then uh that's
how I first studied the diamond cter
Sutra uh so
uh you can do that he says here CH to me
uh trong CH here's the TR chup good day
he says Sub sub means uh be careful when
you go to a family's house to do prayers
uh sub means be
careful so it is true that Lord Buddha
used the diamond way to become a Buddha
in one lifetime it's true and by the way
there's a discussion in the diamond way
text
uh how many Buddhists got to buddhahood
not using Diamond wi and how many
Buddhists got to buddhahood using the
diamond way and the answer
is everybody used the diamond way
there's no Buddha who ever became a
Buddha who didn't use the diamond way to
become a
Buddha so he says here we all know that
this
Buddha um used the diamond way and by
the way he had a spiritual partner and
it's a beautiful beautiful story uh but
uh we all know that he used the diamond
way uh
but J means uh he didn't
trade uh prayers for
buddhahood meaning uh you know he
didn't uh he
didn't the way he practiced Diamond way
he didn't go to people's house and do
Secret mantras so that he could get
lunch okay did he use secret mantras to
become Buddha yes can we use secret
mantras to become Buddha yes did he go
to people's house so and and trade
mantras for for lunch and he says no
okay all right do they do mantras at
people's houses yes does it result in
lunch yes is it for lunch no
okay n here chong chong means don't sell
the Dharma don't sell the Dharma then
people are worried about it people are
like well Gua should we sell Dharma
books should we sell paintings is it
wrong uh it depends that depends on your
motivation okay it's a lousy business
I'll tell you that uh diamonds are
better uh selling the Dharma you know
doesn't pay very well uh I'm just saying
you know it's a lousy business if you
want money for if you want a business
don't sell Dharma so go sell something
sell I don't know jewelry or something
uh it's not a it's not he says here uh
don't sell the Dharma okay don't sell it
can you charge
money here's my answer okay can you
charge can you ask for donations for
your South America tools
or uh you know people always asking me
why you why you sit up there and ask for
donations for diamond mountain which I'm
about to
do uh and my answer
is if you don't want to donate to ACI
for the 303030
program uh then come with me to United
Airlines and I'll come I'll go with you
you know and say look gisha has to get
the
Kyoto uh he's going to teach for
free just give him a seat for free okay
you come with me uh to the United
Airlines travel desk and we'll talk to
them and and they'll
say excuse me they'll say get your crazy
ass out of here you know
and okay there are expenses that we have
and we can't cover them without help you
know we the ACI is free the teaching are
free teachings have always been free uh
but it's a big strain on me and other
people it's a very difficult to to raise
the money and and it wastes our time
it's a huge waste of time uh you know so
I you know it's free everything's free
you don't have to give anything but if
you can help it you we could translate
more books we could do more teachings
you know if you just help the Vietnamese
just uh
donated uh I think 140,000 something
like that to uh to the
volunteer volunteers
coming uh
yeah and the best thing was I I had I
didn't have to ask them they just they
just did you know and I didn't have to
stop my work and and go back for money
so it's not you know the people
organizing those tours
we don't enjoy asking for money and and
it's kind of I don't know you feel kind
of like a prostitute sometimes you know
seriously you're like oh please give me
$10 for this uh teaching you know but
but if you can help it would be nice
okay what are we looking for Tim Tim has
a pro program to keep the ACI teachings
free then uh we have it called 30 3030 I
forget what it is um
if everybody gave $1 a
day uh then we're gonna finish what do
we say 30 years or something like
that huh in seven years we'll
finish
what okay finish the alarm
room that's nine years
honey okay nine
okay yeah
say
again yeah we're going to do a 100 uh
meditation videos okay and uh we're
going to do a 100 videos uh for how to
medit are we doing any this week
any we do one tomorrow maybe we'll do
the first one tomorrow okay uh all
right I think it's a something that we
haven't done very well we have not uh
supplied meditations very well I think
we're doing good on the ancient books
and and all that the L Rim's been steady
but we haven't done
uh we haven't recorded the meditations
so there's about a 100
meditations uh we're going to record a
100 meditations I think we're going to
keep them to half an
hour Tick Tock attention
span
uh yeah I mean it went from 2 hours to 1
hour to 45 to 30 s's asking me to do
five minute things now I'm like S I
can't even start my mouth in five
minutes uh but we'll make them short and
you can use them for the rest of your
life you know you can you'll have a
hundred choices every morning what you
want to meditate guided meditation 100
guided meditations okay uh but we need
help just sign up and shut up sign up
and shut
up okay okay it's $1 a day don't tell me
you can't do that okay so uh if you
please use the QR code and and sign up
and put it on your credit
card you know Jigme wrote me yesterday
you got like 200 subscriptions
to different kinds of Netflix
things and why don't you add
ACI and if there's a really good movie
on a certain streaming service I'm I'm
like okay who cares $ five dollar a
month you know I'll sign up just to see
one movie you know but then after 20
years it's like she's like you think we
should stop this one I'm like
no so just think it's like another
streaming service okay okay so please
help with that all right it's not a big
deal like 30 bucks a month $1 a day okay
and then if we all do it then uh Tim can
fly all around and Aldo and his Mafia
gang they can fly around and help people
okay uh and we can keep it free It's Our
intention to keep it free gisha it's not
free you have to pay to come here I said
that's for the food and that's for the
cabins and but the teaching is free okay
all right
to selling Dharma or trying to get money
out of
Dharma is like asking a king or a queen
to get off the throne and clean the
garbage can know it's not appropriate
okay selling Dharma is like asking the
king or the queen to go clean the toilet
or something you know
it's Chile pup means uh it's like asking
the kid or the queen to get off the
throne and go and go clean the toilet or
something like
that keep your keep your motivation
High uh Tim schedule I start Q&A at 7 is
that
correct for 15 minutes is that correct
okay
means the gift of the Dharma right and
he's focusing here on giving the gift of
the Dharma and he
says uh we're not supposed
to push the Dharma on people I'll tell
you a funny story I think okay people
say gisha you're getting old I say I
know but they say you're repeating the
same stories over and over and I said I
teach every single day around the world
I can't remember which place I taught 12
years ago you know and told a story
so if you are into the diamond way
classes you can think that gesan knows
what he's
doing and he's trying to give you the
story two or three times but if you're
not you can just say he's getting old as
so okay I don't mind uh so anyway now I
forgot what I was going to tell you
story yeah uh yeah okay so I I took the
bus to New York for uh 19 years and and
I could I people tell me I commute for
an hour or I commute for 45 minutes I
commuted for four hours every day for 19
years and uh I didn't want to buy a
car because I wanted to give all the
money to Al Al and uh so I did I gave
all the money to Al and to the monastery
for 19 years and I I took the bus and I
stood out there in in snow storms and
race storms and uh and
I uh I took the so one day uh coming
home the bus
broke uh north of
Freehold and uh it's too far to walk
home it would take a couple hours and uh
it's raining and we stopped and the bus
driver said everybody get out you know
and we're like where and he said there's
a little bar you guys can go in the bar
you know and I'm like oh boy and uh I
went in the bar I called Art I said I
need a ride fast you know so he came to
get me and and I was in the bar and
there was a lady doing go- go in a
bikini on the bar on top of the bar and
I'm like you know and uh and there all
these guys sitting there getting drunk
you know and I was reading this this
part of the L rim and I thought well he
says whenever you're sitting with
anybody try to bring up the Dharma in a
in a skillful way you know start looking
all these drunk guys and the ladies like
dancing and I'm like did you ever hear
about
Dharma and uh you can
always you know if you're skillful you
can always teach something okay you can
always talk about something so you know
think about it when you're in the bar
and the go go
bar uh you can always
think of something to help people right
and uh that's a bodh safas activity
that's bu sufferance activity okay
Wherever You Are by accident then use
the time don't waste your time and try
to learn something or try to speak
something the Buddha we had it yesterday
in
the we did a ritual yesterday there's 60
uh songs of the Buddhist speech
sometimes they say 60 and one of them is
to be able to talk to anybody in their
language so uh you can try to learn bar
talk go go bar talk what's the guys
doing you know what's up with the
football game you know and then you know
do you know you have to die sometime
so you can always there's always some
kind of Dharma thing you can say okay
and and we're supposed to learn these
learn to speak
SAS what's that we're supposed to learn
to speak in all people's languages right
SAS it doesn't mean Russian Spanish
Japanese it means B talk goobar do
goobar
dialect and uh learn to speak to people
in their own language okay and that's a
that's a skill of a bodh
[Music]
okay uh R chungi now those of you who
are monks and nuns in in Tibet in
1920 okay uh
CH actually you're kind of limited to
Dharma the giving you can do is Dharma
giving because monks and nuns aren't
supposed to carry money or they're not
supposed to own
things and I think it got corrupted in
in recent years in my Monastery
everybody kind of owns their own house
they own their own apartment they pass
it on to the next to their student uh so
really there is private
property and I think it's not a good
system the tantry
college G where where my teacher was uh
like vice president or something he
there you cannot own your room you don't
own your room you have to move every 3
months uh you cannot stay in one room
more than three months uh and they force
you to move to another
room uh in the Sarah uh it it's pretty
much private property you own your you
own your Monk's apartment and you pass
it on to your friends or your students
but supposed to be that monks and nuns
don't possess things like that uh chin
so the main kind of giving for monk or a
n is the Dharma okay they to B Jonah B
Jonah I uh
right B J means if it comes to you
easily if people give you a lot of money
if people hand you a red envelope with
$10,000 in it bade Jonah and you didn't
ask for it they just gave it to you okay
then you can you can as a monk or a nun
you can share what you have you can
share the money with other people you
can give the money to other people okay
um okay
Rami sh uh there's a
Kad
name second
generation I like this one he says uh
I'm not trying to sell you on the
benefits of sharing what you have p mij
mij means I'm not trying to convince you
of the benefits of sharing what you
have I'm trying to convince you that it
hurts you to keep
things okay and that's cool I think he
says I'm not trying to get you to to
donate money to
ACI I'm just telling you if you keep it
it'll hurt you okay it's interesting if
you if you keep it
if you think you can keep it by keeping
it you're hurting yourself you keep it
by giving it you see what I mean okay do
I like money
yes I don't buy things I don't I have
old car old house old clothes they just
sewed it up while I was in
to not very
well and uh but if I get money I like to
use it I like to use you know I like to
print a new book or I like to build a
build a new cabin at di mountain or
something like that okay so he says
here I'm not trying to convince you to
make a donation to
ACI I'm not trying to get you
to to appreciate the act of
giving I'm trying to convince you that
keeping things is a stupid
strategy okay when you keep things I had
a friend in the diamond business Jane a
Jane
monk uh in
Mumbai and he he started a business
Diamond business he we started it
together in India and and he became one
of the largest in the world and and he
said he used to say Michael money likes
to move money likes to move you
shouldn't keep money in a bank account
or you shouldn't hold it in your pocket
you should let it move money wants to
flow and then it will help more people
okay so he says here this kadam pishi
you know I'm not trying to convince you
to be
generous I'm just saying what a drag it
is to sit on money and then you're G to
die anyway you know then that money has
to go looking for a new owner it's just
stupid you know don't let money sit
there doing nothing uh while you sit on
it and then you die and it didn't help
anybody okay money was
useless sometimes it flows too fast
that's
okay you know sometimes my wife's like
we can't pay the bills I'm like yeah
we'll work it out you know so it's
better to let it flow too fast than to
hold it okay holding it is
really holding it is is stupid and if
everybody held their money then
everybody would be poor you see what I
mean we have to let money flow okay when
it comes then let
let it flow okay and then it then
everyone's benefit
okay all right we're going to pause
there and do
Q&A and you please don't hit anybody
with the
box and by the way if you need to go to
the bathroom or something feel free okay
um so gu the first question is from
online and it's it's kind of a fun
difficult question and wondering if you
could explain the how we move from the
fifth flavor of emptiness The Fifth
Fifth flavor of emptiness oh to the
sixth flavor of
emptiness and and how like how
dependence is different in those two so
so we can help our students understand
those differences
yeah yeah there's
um the difference between the two forms
of emptiness inside the middle way
school okay lower middle way and higher
middle way so uh pranga higher middle
way and the independent I like to call
it the two groups inside of the
of the middle W
co uh the lower middle way which would
be five world view number five uh they
believe that basically you can think of
it that we are interpreting the world
okay so how the world seems to you is an
interpretation so different people get
different uh raw data okay raw data like
I don't know there's a a glass of pink
liquid okay and then the raw data
according to the lower middle way is the
same for everybody in this room there's
a there's a cup of pink liquid and
that's from the other side not from my
side but from the other side there's raw
data appear to me okay uh and and that's
a pink color and a cup shape okay and
then I interpret the raw data if I'm
uh you know I don't know if I'm trying
to be healthy it happens to be almond
milk and strawberry okay zero carbs both
of
them
um and then I don't know uh to somebody
else it might if you don't know what it
is I don't know I've many people online
I mean people I get all kinds of emails
they say why you drinking a
margarita you know in class you know no
really you have no idea by the way when
you step into the role of a Dharma
teacher get ready to be
patient uh because people will say all
kinds of terrible things about guess I
was drinking margarin in class you know
and um
so somebody looks at the same liquid and
they see a margarita and and that tells
us more about the person than about
gisha you know what I mean if you see a
margarita maybe you're drinking
margaritas not me but um so in the lower
middle
way uh everybody has a certain set of
seeds and there's raw data there is a
pink liquid in this room and that wasn't
made by
anybody gisha just held it up you know
I'm not making the pink liquid the pink
liquid is
there how I interpret it how I take it
that's the emptiness you know if I have
been drinking margaritas a lot then I
will think gisha has a margarita and if
I've been on a diet for too
long 9 kilos of I'll teach you a trick
um you know if you've been on a diet for
a long time then then you're like oh
that's some kind of you know healthy
drink you know like that so in the lower
Middle Way worldview number
five uh people are interpreting raw data
which is out there the out the raw data
is really there and then we interpret it
in different ways and that's the
emptiness okay The Emptiness of this
pink liquid
is that it could be an almond drink or
it could be a margarita that depends on
your seats but the pink liquid does not
depend on your seeds pink liquid is raw
data we all experiencing a pink liquid
no matter what's our Karma everyone's
experiencing a color and a shape okay
that's fifth School fifth fifth
worldview sixth worldview is even the
rod that is coming from you
even the pink liquid is coming from you
there's many people who would not see
pink and there's many people who would
not see a liquid there's many people who
might see this as a as a knife or
something okay there's no reason to
say just because it's pink that the Pink
is coming from its own side and and the
highest the highest middle way six sixth
world view says that even the raw data
is coming from from me you know that
that if you had different karmic
seeds you wouldn't even see pink you
would see and you wouldn't see a cup
shape you would see a different shape
and you would see a different color
everything about your perceptions is
coming from your seats there's nothing
coming from its own s not even the the
pink color not even the shape okay
you're making that also okay and and
that's that's that's the difference
between five and six okay and as you go
higher through the six flavors of
emptiness they become more
allinclusive and they help you more okay
if you can understand that even the
colors you see are coming from you uh
you'll be a better person you you you'll
be you'll be sweeter to other people
even the colors are are coming from you
everything is coming from you there's
nothing about another
person even their the color of their
face their eyes their lips that's not
coming from you everything's your
fault okay every excuse me but every
you ever met was a direct
reflection of you then that gets a
little overwhelming you're like everyone
you know like that boyfriend in sixth
grade yeah okay everything even the
colors are coming from you okay much
less how they act and stuff like that
okay cool that's the difference between
five is the fifth one
okay they would say if the state of mind
is not affected by alcohol or Insanity
or you know
sickness that raw data is out there by
its own uh that's the fifth world view
okay there's
a there's a small print that says the
Mind should be unaffected it should be
not crazy not drunk not insane then that
raw data is coming from its own
side cool
next
yeah thank you for teaching and the
first of the six perception the first
one is giving sharing and the first one
four magnets sharing two so what's the
difference between these two I'm sorry
say again oh the first of the six
perception setion is sharing yeah and
the first one of the full magnet is also
sharing oh yeah yeah okay got it yeah
okay
good uh by the way Sophie Chow organized
a beautiful talk
with we she and I talked to
Marie
Co who invented this uh
neatness program in Japan and uh we had
a really good time and uh I think it was
an hour or something and the three of us
did a talk together and if you get a
chance you should see it I think it's
kind of fun to see uh such a
disorganized GUI talking about talking
with such an organized
people uh but it was a beautiful uh it
was a beautiful time interview that we
had and we might do it again in Kyoto or
something I think
anyway for the first of the four magnets
or ways of attracting disciples is to
attract them with material things you
know so if you
want when you're
ready uh you should attract students and
the first thing is to help them
financially you know uh or offer
them you know always by the way your
Latin America Tour guys the key is
Donuts you know to get a get people to
come to your talk it's Refreshments okay
and and that's just uh if you want to
attract students then uh the first
rule uh is to be generous and uh feed
them and I I uh the the original ACI
course s years I paid for everything for
seven years and it was hard it was
really hard and uh but you should if you
want to be a
teacher uh in the beginning to to to to
get people to come to class be generous
be overly generous you know get some
money uh have good ref don't have cheap
stupid Refreshments have high quality
refreshments and U you know spend some
time thinking about it spend some effort
uh to help your student students and if
a student is broke or a student is
having a financial problem or then help
them okay and this is the first step to
being a teacher is to be willing to help
your students financially and physically
okay whatever they need uh help them
help them take care of it okay
um what's the difference between that
and the first Perfection I would say it
is the first Perfection I'd say it's
when we talk about the
four methods of attracting
disciples the give it's the same giving
it's the same Perfection of giving but
in the short term the goal of the giving
is to attract people to class and to get
people to come to your class or
something like that and then the first
Perfection is more General it's all
kinds of giving actually you're in the
first Perfection you're still trying to
get people to come to your class but in
10,000
years like when he gave his body to the
tiger it's the same thing as giving
Donuts to the first students who come to
your class but U little bit longer
timeline and then uh the the first of
the four magnets is it's very it is also
the Perfection of giving yeah that's
true that's true but it's short term
purposes to attract the students you and
don't be shy about it you know
be that's that's the way things are
that's the way the world is you know
then spend some time make sure you have
high quality Refreshments make sure you
have a lot you know make sure you're
ready to clean up afterwards because
they will not help you and uh and just
relax and have fun and you're like mommy
your mommy doesn't say look do you know
how many breasts full of milk I gave you
already why you want more you know uh
moms don't ask that question they just
give and so a Dharma teacher should just
keep giving okay and don't don't don't
get don't get weird about it just keep
giving you know keep giving that's
that's the business we're in that's what
we do cool